Finding Aid for Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore Extended Occupancy Rights Group
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore Extended Occupancy Rights Group records
Late 1960s-2015
1990s
Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore Extended Occupancy Rights Group
2.25 linear feet in 3 boxes
2016007 Bz 2
The Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore Extended Occupancy Rights Group (SBDNL) records collected by Paul and JoAnne Wheaton. SBDNL was a group of residents of Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore who were interested in seeking to extend or modify their lease arrangements with the National Park Service. The collection consists of documents pertaining to information about the residents of Sleeping Bear and their property, legal documentation, and media and news sources regarding the issue, as well as a large number of photos.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by JoAnee Wheaton (donor no. 11272 ) in June, 2015.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
The Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore is located in the northwest of the lower peninsula of Michigan in Leelanau and Benzie counties, on the coast of Lake Michigan and near Empire. Famous for its stunning vistas and historic farmland, its designation as a national lakeshore sparked a controversy between the residents of the lakeshore and the National Park Service. The national lakeshore was first proposed by Senator Philip Hart of Michigan in 1961 and the bill creating it was passed in 1970. Under the bill, any property built prior to 1964 was permitted to remain on the park grounds and expand as desired. Properties erected between 1964 and 1970, however, were condemned and their owners to be given monetary settlements.
Facing eviction, many property owners formed a group called Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore Extended Occupancy Rights Group (SBDNL) with the goal of acquiring either life leases on their homes or extensions on their leaseback period. The group included Ron Eckert as president, and Paul and JoAnne Wheaton as vice-president and secretary, respectively. As secretary, JoAnne collected much of the paper material generated and used by the group from its founding. Around ninety residents signed commitment forms to the group.
Prior to the 1970 bill, it had been the precedent to extend occupancy rights to ninety nine years for lease holders whose property fell within a newly-formed national park. The Sleeping Bear Dunes Lakeshore residents were given a leaseback period of five years before their property would be destroyed. Many homeowners whose property satisfied the pre-1964 cutoff opted to leave despite their exemption, and many of these homes form the historic farmlands of the park.
The SBDNL Extended Occupancy Rights group sought the advice and legal representation of Grand Rapids lawyers, appealed to Senator Hart and other legislatures, and made their case publically known through local media outlets. By taking their case to court, many residents, including the Wheatons, were able to extend their lease by thirty five years, ending in 2005. After this period, most of the structures were bulldozed in an attempt to preserve the natural condition of the area.
The collection is arranged into three series: Resident Files, Legal Files, and Media.
The Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore Extended Occupancy Rights Group Records contain the paperwork and photos accumulated by Paul and JoAnne Wheaton dating from the mid 1960's to 2015. Included are records of membership in the Extended Rights Group, legal files pertaining to court cases and legislation, and media coverage of the issue. Numerous photographs of properties destroyed by the National Park Service are present in the collection.
Subjects:
Homeowners' associations--Michigan--Leelanau County.; Land use--Michigan--Leelanau County.; National parks and reserves--Michigan--Leelanau County.; Right of property--Michigan--Leelanau County.; Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore (Mich.); Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore Extended Occupancy Rights Group.; United States. National Park Service. Midwest Region.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Houses--Michigan--Leelanau County.
Contributors:
Wheaton, JoAnne.; Wheaton, Paul.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Resident Files
  The Resident Files series (1.5 linear feet) contains individual folders for each committed member of the SBDNL Extended Occupancy Rights group, background information on the topic provided by JoAnne Wheaton, the group's financial information, correspondence among members, administrative documents of their meetings, and a plethora of photographs of residencies and properties both occupied and deserted.
  - Background information, 2015 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1993-1997; 11 folders (Box 1)
  - Individual resident files, 1994-1995; 100 folders (Box 1)
  - Financial information,1997-1998, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Membership information, 1983-1999; 18 folders (Box 2)
  - Photographs of properties, 1996-2000; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Related cases, 1971-1999; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - SBDNL administration files, 1995-1997; 3 folders (Box 2)
- Legal Files
  Within the Legal Files (0.5 linear feet) series will be found information on and correspondence with the attorneys involved with the case. Pertinent legislation is supplied along with research carried out by the group on the law affecting their case. The oversize folder contains additional legal information, largely records of business with the group's lawyers.
  - Attorneys, 1984-2000(8 folders) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1994-1998(5 folders) (Box 2)
  - Legislature, 1961-1997(11 folders) (Box 2)
  - Research, 1997-1999; 9 folders (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1979-1981 (Folder 1)
- Media
  The Media series (0.25 linear feet) is majority newspaper clippings of stories about the group or the Sleeping Bear Dunes in general. Additionally, a few folders are included that relate to media contact information or involvement.
  - Clippings, 1994-1999; 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Other media, 1995-1999; 3 folders (Box 3)
Related material
Loren S. and Marjorie Rabe Barritt Collection at the Bentley Historical Library.